A Guide to the Emily Lee Papers, 1943-2001
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
Emily Lee Papers1943-2001
Special Collections, James Madison University
5007
2 boxes (1 linear foot)
The collection includes James Madison University related correspondence, newsclippings, photographs, scrapbooks, interview, and reunion booklets.
Emily Lee Lewis
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Received from Alumni Relations May, 2003
Biographical Information
Emily Lewis Lee graduated from Madison College as part of the class of 1943 with a degree in Home Economics. After graduation, she entered Johns Hopkins in Baltimore to begin a six month internship, after which she completed another six months at Halloran Hospital on Staten Island. She then entered the Army Medical Corps as a dietician and was trained in Atlantic City. She met her husband, Luther Lee, while stationed in North Carolina when she was a first lieutenant. She was discharged from the army at the end of the war, and later on became a dietician at the Veterans Administration hospital. Since then has been a proud and active alumni of her alma mater. Emily Lee has served on the Alumni Association, the Education and Student Life Committee, the Board of Visitors from 1980-1983, and as the fund agent for the class of 1943. In 1981, she received the "Distinguished Alumni Service Award" for her work for the university.
Scope and Content
This collection documents Emily Lee's work with James Madison University's Alumni Association, the Board of Visitors, attendance at JMU events, and reunions with her classmates. Much of her correspondence includes letters to her fellow alumnae from the class of 1943. Her awards, appointments and accompanying news clippings are included as are booklets compiled for alumni reunion weekends and homecomings. Of special interest is the history of the university's processional mace, a gift of the Class of 1943, presented to the University on Founder's Day, 1979. Of more recent interest are a 2001 interview with journalist Nancy Bondurant Jones and two subsequent articles on World War II and plans for an Alumni Center Terrace to honor JMU's contribution to it. Many photographs are included that document reunions and special celebrations at James Madison University.
Series 1, Correspondence, 1953- (1973-1983)-2001 and undated, contains letters mainly regarding reunion planning, plus Lee's annual "Lee News" bulletins for 1981, 1983-1991, with similar reports in 1997, 1999 and 2001.
Series 2, Scrapbooks and Guestbooks, contains two large scrapbooks largely of color photographs compiled either for or after the 35th, 40th and 45th Reunions of the Class of '43. The first of these has a small selection of black & white photographs from the 1940s. The three smaller guestbooks contain signatures from alumni receptions and luncheons dating from 1956-1989. The first of these books belonged to the Madison Alumni Richmond Chapter, and the other two are most likely from on-campus alumni events.
Series 3, Ephemera, contains a clipping about Mrs. Lee from the "Alumni Bulletin" Vol. 2, No. 1; the "Home Economics Alumni Newletter," No. 17, December 1981 with front page coverage of Mrs. Lee receiving an alumni service award; reunion booklets from the 1978 and 1979; and an undated alumni publication, "From Blue Stone Hill to You," among other programs and flyers. Included here are an interview with Nancy B. Jones (March 15, 2001), and Jones' article in the Harrisonburg Daily News Record on April 17 and in the JMU Alumni magazine Montpelier in Summer, 2001.
Series 4, University Mace, concerns the university's processional mace and includes a letter from the artist, Prof. Ron Wyancko, newsclippings, fundraising for the Mace Fund, and notes on the Founder's Day processional 1978-1979.
Series 5, Photographs, contains a 5x7" b&w print of Emily Lee presenting the mace to President Carrier in 1979, an 8x10" of her reunion group ca. 1983 and four snap shots of awards and reunion banquets from the early 1980s. Also includes photographs from 10 scrapbooks documenting reunions and events, as well as graduation photos from her commencement in 1943.This series is broken up into three subseries (Original Collection Photos, Reunions, and University Events) which are in turn broken down into several subseries.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 5 series and 3 subseries:
I: Correspondence, 1953-2001, undated
II: Scrapbooks and Guest Books, 1956, 1974-1989
III: Ephemera, 1956, 1978-1983
IV: University Mace, 1978-1979
V: Photographs
Subseries 1. Original Collection Photos
Subseries 2. Reunions
Subseries 3. University Events
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1953-2001, undated (Box-folder 1:1)
- Scrapbooks and Guestbooks
  - Scrapbook 1, 1942-1986 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1980-1989 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Guestbook 1 (1956-1979) and Guestbook 2 (1977-1989) (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Guestbook 3, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Ephemera, 1956-2001, undated (Box-folder 2:2)
- University Mace, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2:3)
- University Mace, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Photographs
  - Original Collection (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Emily Lee presenting the University Mace to Dr. Carrier, Image 5007.05.0001
    - Emily Lee and reunion group, Image 5007.05.0002
    - Four snapshots of Emily Lee>, Image 5007.05.0003
  - Original Collection (Box-folder 2:4)
    - 1995 and 1996 '43 Madison group reunion (Box-folder 2:5)
      - Cover photo, Image 5007.05.0004
      - Flower display, Image 5007.05.0005
      - Garden Club shirt, Image 5007.05.0006
      - Emily Lee with Frances Agnor Traver and Ann Valentine Pheiffer, Image 5007.05.0007
      - "The Gang" group shot, Image 5007.05.0008
      - Til Purnell w/ horse, Image 5007.05.0009
      - At stable, group shot, Image 5007.05.0010
      - Tea Room Lunch, group shot, Image 5007.05.0011
      - Group at dinner, Image 5007.05.0012
      - Mary Jackson, Ann Valentine Pheiffer, Ethel Mason Miller, Frances Agnor Traver, and unidentified woman, Image 5007.05.0013
      - Dick and Frances Traver with Ruth Anne Herring, Image 5007.05.0014
      - Dick Traver and Ruth Anne Herring, Image 5007.05.0015
      - Space Shuttle at Cape Canaveral, Image 5007.05.0016
      - Cape Canaveral, group shot, Image 5007.05.0017
      - Group next to space shuttle, Image 5007.05.0018
      - Ladies out shopping, Image 5007.05.0019
      - Catharine Cothran Pedigo, Mary Jackson, Ethel Mason Moore, Frances Agnor Traver, Ann Valentine Pheiffer, Image 5007.05.0020
      - Group in front of restaurant, Image 5007.05.0021
      - Emily Lee, Frances Agnor Traver, Mary Jackson, Catharine Cothran Pedigo at Lee Chapel, Image 5007.05.0022
      - Emily Lee, Margaret Hoffman Gouldman, and Marcella Mears, Image 5007.05.0023
      - Frances Agnor Traver, Mary Jackson, Margaret Hoffman Gouldman, Emily Lee, Catharine Cothran Pedigo, Image 5007.05.0024
      - Emily Lee, Margaret Hoffman Gouldman, Catharine Cothran Pedigo, Frances Agnor Traver, Mary Jackson, Image 5007.05.0025
      - RV at campground, Image 5007.05.0026
      - Group in motor home, Image 5007.05.0027
      - Group shot at dinner, Image 5007.05.0028
      - Group at dinner, Image 5007.05.0029
      - Frances Agnor Traver, Image 5007.05.0030
      - Emily Lee and Ethel Mason Miller, Image 5007.05.0031
      - Louise and Bud Hansby, Dick Traver, Image 5007.05.0032
      - Frances Agnor Traver, Mary Jackson, Til Horn Purnell, Ann Valentine Pheiffer, Ethel Mason Miller, Image 5007.05.0033
    - 1997 and 1998 '43 Madison group reunion (Box-folder 2:5)
      - Cover photo, Emily Lee, Image 5007.05.0034
      - Til Horn Purnell, Ethel Mason Moore, Ann Valentine Pheiffer, Image 5007.05.0035
      - Making memory books, Image 5007.05.0036
      - Ladies with scrapbooks, Image 5007.05.0037
      - In front of Poplar Forest., Image 5007.05.0038
      - Emily Lee, Ann Valentine Pheiffer, and unidentified woman, Image 5007.05.0039
      - Ann Valentine Pheiffer, Ethel Mason Miller, Dick Traver, Image 5007.05.0040
      - Group shot at table, Image 5007.05.0041
      - By lake at Peaks of Otter, Image 5007.05.0042
      - Avoca-Ancestral home of Col. Lynch, Image 5007.05.0043
      - Group in front of house, Image 5007.05.0044
      - Anne and Don Pheiffer, Image 5007.05.0045
      - Betty's Kitchen, Image 5007.05.0046
      - Appomatox Battleground, Image 5007.05.0047
      - Ladies waiting to eat, Image 5007.05.0048
      - The husbands, Image 5007.05.0049
      - Ann and Don Pheiffer with nephew, Image 5007.05.0050
      - Frances Agnor Traver and Til Horn Purnell, Image 5007.05.0051
      - Til Horn Purnell and Frances Agnor Traver, Image 5007.05.0052
      - Mary and Tom Sweet wedding photo, Image 5007.05.0053
      - Ladies with Van Reese, Image 5007.05.0054
      - "The men arrive", Image 5007.05.0055
      - Dick Traver, Image 5007.05.0056
      - Waiting in front of Olive Garden, Image 5007.05.0057
      - Ethel Mason Miller and husband?, Image 5007.05.0058
      - Lunch at Williamsburg Inn, Image 5007.05.0059
      - Music at Williamsburg Inn, Image 5007.05.0060
      - More music, Image 5007.05.0061
      - Mary Jackson and Til Horn Purnell, Image 5007.05.0062
      - Emily Lee with Mary Jackson and Frances Agnor Traver, Image 5007.05.0063
      - Entertainment at tavern, Image 5007.05.0064
      - Group at dinner, Image 5007.05.0065
      - Comfort suites, Image 5007.05.0066
    - 1999 '43 Madison group reunion (Box-folder 2:5)
      - Emily Lee with the Vanlandinghaw's, Image 5007.05.0067
      - Catharine Cothran Pedigo, Mary Jackson, Ann Valentine Pheiffer, Image 5007.05.0068
      - Ethel Mason Miller, Frances Agnor Traver, and Marion Watkins Herger, Image 5007.05.0069
      - Frances Traver, Ethel Mason Miller, Ann Brown Hutchinson, Catharine Cothran Pedigo, Image 5007.05.0070
      - Emily Lee with Virginia Tunnes Wells, Image 5007.05.0071
      - Priceless Tiffany Window, Image 5007.05.0072
      - Ethel Mason Miller, Catharine Cothran Pedigo, Ann Valentine Pheiffer, Frances Agnor Traver, Image 5007.05.0073
      - Table at dinner, Image 5007.05.0074
      - Music at farewell dinner, Image 5007.05.0075
      - Emily Lee, Mary Jackson, Ann Valentine Pheiffer, Catharine Cothran Pedigo, Ethel Mason Miller, Frances Agnor Traver, Image 5007.05.0076
      - Robin Worth and wife Joann, Image 5007.05.0077
      - Emily Lee with group at dinner, Image 5007.05.0078
      - Group at happy hour, Image 5007.05.0079
      - Ladies in front of Petersburg Country Club, Image 5007.05.0080
      - Carriage Tour of Olde Towne, Image 5007.05.0081>
    - 2000 '43 Madison group reunion (Box-folder 2:6)
      - Weighing-in at Marina, Image 5007.05.0082
      - Ann Valentine Pheiffer and Don Pheiffer, Image 5007.05.0083
      - Marina, Image 5007.05.0084
      - Frances and Don Traver, Image 5007.05.0085
      - Marge Hoskins and Mary Jackson on front porch, Image 5007.05.0086
      - Emily Lee and Mary Jackson, Image 5007.05.0087
      - Emily Lee and group at Beaufort Chamber of Commerce, Image 5007.05.0088
      - Group on carriage ride, Image 5007.05.0089
      - Marge Hoskins and husband, Image 5007.05.0090
      - Chicago painted cow, Image 5007.05.0091
      - Group in front of buses, Image 5007.05.0092
      - Emily Lee, Marge Hoskins, Frances Traver, Don Traver, Image 5007.05.0093
      - Emily Lee, Marge Hoskins, Mary Jackson, Image 5007.05.0094
      - Emily Lee with Marge Hoskins and Mary Jackson, Image 5007.05.0095
      - Frances Agnor Traver, Mary Jackson, Ann Valentine Pheiffer, Image 5007.05.0096
      - Marge Hoskins, Bob Hoskins, Dick Traver, Frances Agnor Traver, Image 5007.05.0097
      - Group shot on porch, Image 5007.05.0098
      - Til Horn Purnell, Frances Agnor Traver, Mary Jackson, Ann Valentine Phieffer, Emily Lewis Lee, Image 5007.05.0099
      - "Dolphin Watch" house, Image 5007.05.0100
      - Frances Traver, Mary Jackson, Ann Valentine Pheiffer, Dick Traver, Image 5007.05.0101
      - Marge Hoskins, Image 5007.05.0102
      - Emily Lee and Sigma sisters with Sigma plaque, Image 5007.05.00103
      - Sunrise from front porch, Image 5007.05.0104
      - Mary Jackson and others saying goodbye, Image 5007.05.0105
      - Waving goodbye, Image 5007.05.0106
      - Ann and Don Phieffer, Image 5007.05.0107
    - 2001 '43 Madison group reunion (Box-folder 2:6)
      - Cover photo, Image 5007.05.0108
      - Til Purnell with dog, Kipley, and car, Image 5007.05.0109
      - Catharine Cothran Pedigo, Frances Agnor Traver, Mary Jackson, Ethel Mason Moore, Image 5007.05.0110
      - Men group shot, Image 5007.05.0111
      - Emily Lee, Image 5007.05.0112
      - Til Purnell with Margaret Hoffman Gouldman, Image 5007.05.0113
      - Mary Jackson, Frances Agnor Traver, Ethel Mason Moore, Image 5007.05.0114
      - Dick Traver, Hart Miller, Tom Sweet, Image 5007.05.0115
      - Hart Miller, others at table, Image 5007.05.0116
      - Group at dinner, Image 5007.05.0117
      - Mary Jackson and Til Purnell, Image 5007.05.0118
      - Skip Purnell reviews appointment calendar, Image 5007.05.0119
      - Charlisa Howell, Frances Traver, Til Purnell, Image 5007.05.0120
      - Frances Traver, Til Purnell, Margaret Hoffman Gouldman, Image 5007.05.0121
      - Group with Charlisa Howell, Dick Traver, Frances Traver, Image 5007.05.0122
      - The whole group, Image 5007.05.0123
      - Frances Agnor Traver, Image 5007.05.0124
      - Til and Skip Purnell, Image 5007.05.0125
      - Emily Lee and Til Purnell, Image 5007.05.0126
      - Emily Lee and Til Purnell, Image 5007.05.0127
      - Til Purnell, Image 5007.05.0128
      - High school group, Image 5007.05.0129
      - Margaret Hoffman Gouldman, Image 5007.05.0130
      - Margaret Hoffman Gouldman, Image 5007.05.0131
      - "Rhodendedrem" Bush, Image 5007.05.0132
        Picture of Rhododendron Bushes is labeled "beautiful rhodedendrem [sic] everywhere"
  - University Events
    - 1943 Commencement Ceremony (Box-folder 2:7)
      - Graduation ceremony, Image 5007.05.0133
      - Emily Lewis Lee with diploma, Image 5007.05.0134
      - Emily Lewis lee and group in front of Jackson Hall, Image 5007.05.0135
      - Emily Lewis Lee and group, Image 5007.05.0136
      - Emily Lewis Lee and large group, Image 5007.05.0137
      - Emily Lewis Lee and other graduates, Image 5007.05.0138
      - Emily Lewis lee and others, Image 5007.05.0139
    - Class of 1943 35th reunion 1973 (Box-folder 2:7)
      - Midge and Nate Clark, Image 5007.05.0140
      - Emily Lee and two others, Image 5007.05.0141
      - Emily Lee and friends, Image 5007.05.0142
      - Margaret Hoffman Gouldman, Image 5007.05.0143
      - At table, Dr. Carrier in background, Image 5007.05.0144
      - Frances Agnor Traver, Ann Valentine Phieffer and others, Image 5007.05.0145
      - Emily Lee and others in front of hotel, Image 5007.05.0146
      - In front of hotel, Image 5007.05.0147
    - Inauguration of President Linwood Rose - Sept 1999 (Box-folder 2:7)
      - Harrisonburg sign from Massanutten, '98, Image 5007.05.0148
      - Emily Lee with Rebecca Davidson ('47) and members of the Rose family, Image 5007.05.0149
      - Rebecca Davidson with Jane Dingledine Houston ('42), Image 5007.05.0150
      - Sunset from "New Campus", Image 5007.05.0151
      - Emily Lee, Kathy Jasien, and Rebecca Davidson at dinner, Image 5007.05.0152
      - Dr. Douglas Brown, VP Academic Affairs, with Betsy Brown, Bill and Kathy Jasien at dinner, Image 5007.05.0153
      - Bonnie Neff Hoover and Stanley Folk at dinner, Image 5007.05.0154
      - Campus painting being presented to the Carriers', Image 5007.05.0155
      - Edith Carrier with painting, Image 5007.05.0156
      - Emily Lee and Rebecca Davidson with 90's Tri Sigma t-shirt, Image 5007.05.0157
      - Jane Kinderman and Rebecca Bennett Davidson at Walton House, Image 5007.05.0158
      - Group shot at Strawderman '87, Image 5007.05.0159
      - roup shot, Richmond Fall '94, Image 5007.05.0160
      - Emily Lee and group, Petersburg Fall '94, Image 5007.05.0161
      - Peggy A. and family, Image 5007.05.0162
      - Emily Virginia Lewis, '40, Image 5007.05.0163
    - Alumni Weekend - May 2002 (Box-folder 2:8)
      - Alumni Weekend 2002 cover, Image 5007.05.0164
      - Baseball field, Image 5007.05.0165
      - Emily Lee with VCU coach's wife, Image 5007.05.0166
      - Emily Lee with JMU player's parents, Image 5007.05.0167
      - Wilson Hall, Image 5007.05.0168
      - Emily Lee with '52 alum dressed as clown and husband, Image 5007.05.0169
      - Emily Lee with Emily Long Bruce and Lois Long on bench by Kissing Rock, Image 5007.05.0170
      - Lucille June Smead, Image 5007.05.0171
      - Kathy Stafford, VP for Development, outside of Alumnae Hall, Image 5007.05.0172
      - Emily Lee with her weekend escort Catharine Cook, Image 5007.05.0173
      - Two '52 alumni at reception at President Rose's house, Image 5007.05.0174
      - Emily Lee with Nellie Long, Ralph and Inez Roop, Image 5007.05.0175
      - Emily Lee and Georgina Chapplear Milleken, Image 5007.05.0176
      - Catharine Cook and driver Mr. Roberts with JMU bus, Image 5007.05.0177
      - Emily Lee and Polly Long, Image 5007.05.0178
      - Emily Lee with Evelyn Jefferson and Lillian Bundy and others at 1942 table, Image 5007.05.0179
      - JMU flowers by Festival, Image 5007.05.0180
      - Emily Lee and Glenda Bennett (Sigma sisters) in front of Bluestone fireplace in Alumnae Hall, Image 5007.05.0181
      - Emily Lee with Justin Thompson, Director of Alumni Relations, Image 5007.05.0182
      - Emily Lee and Nancy Bondurant Jones, Image 5007.05.0183
      - Emily Lee and Nancy Bondurant Jones, Image 5007.05.0184
      - Carolyn Copley during candle ceremony, Image 5007.05.0185
      - Emily Lee with Ann Dechert and Nancy Hughes, Image 5007.05.0186
      - Emily Lee and others, Image 5007.05.0187
    - Alumni Weekend - May 2002 (Box-folder 2:8)
      - Emily Lee with Anna Long Watson and Emily Long Bruce, picture of Bonnie Heff attached, Image 5007.05.0188
      - Emily Lee and Bob Hoskins, Image 5007.05.0189
      - Emily Lee and Marge Hoskins, Image 5007.05.0190
      - Emily Lee and Margaret Moore, Image 5007.05.0191
      - Emily Lee with Sigma sisters in front of Sigma house, Image 5007.05.0192
      - Emily Lee with Sigmas and Cake Walk t-shirt, Image 5007.05.0193
      - Emily Lee with Sigma alumni and current officers, Image 5007.05.0194
      - Emily Lee with replica of Leeolou Alumni Center, Image 5007.05.0195
      - Emily Lee with List of Lead Donors, Image 5007.05.0196
      - Emily Long Bruce, Lisa Horsch, Steph Ann Watson, Marge Hoskins at Dedication Dinner, Image 5007.05.0197
      - Emily Lee, Ann Watson, Marge Hoskins at table, Image 5007.05.0198
      - Emily Lee with President Rose and wife Judith, Image 5007.05.0199
      - Emily Lee and Mike Dewitt from JMU Board of Visitors, Image 5007.05.0200
      - Emily Lee with the Rose's, the McGraw's, and Lucy Koof-Pust at post-game reception, Image 5007.05.0201
      - Emily Lee, Marge Hoskins, and friend at reception, Image 5007.05.0202
      - Emily Lee and Marge Hoskins on parking deck at reception, Image 5007.05.0203
      - JMU flowers by Leeolou Alumni Center, Image 5007.05.0204
      - Front of Leeolou Alumni Center, Image 5007.05.0205
      - Emily Lee and Lisa Horsch at Bridgeforth Stadium, Image 5007.05.0206
      - Emily Lee and field at Bridgeforth Stadium, Image 5007.05.0207
      - "Welcome Back Alumni!" sign at Leeolou Alumni Center, Image 5007.05.0208
      - Emily Lee and Lisa Horsch with Madison scrapbook, Image 5007.05.0209
      - Emily Lee, Lisa Horsch, Marge Hoskins at WWII Garden Patio, Image 5007.05.0210
      - Emily Lee and Lisa Horsch with Veterans of WWII plaque, Image 5007.05.0211
    - James Madison Day Celebrations - March 2006 (Box-folder 2:8)
      - Emily Lee and Marge Hoskins at graves of Emily and Mable Lee Walton, Image 5007.05.0212
      - Emily Lee with Ass. VP for Constituent Relations, Image 5007.05.0213
      - Emily Lee with Marge Hoskins and Director of Development Karen Guntharp, Image 5007.05.0214
      - Emily Lee with Dr. Phyllis Rowe, Image 5007.05.0215
      - Emily Lee with hostess and staff, Image 5007.05.0216
      - Emily Lee with Jane Dingledine Houston, Image 5007.05.0217
      - Emily Lee with Carolyn Wakr, Image 5007.05.0218
      - View of Wilson stage for Madison Day Program, Image 5007.05.0219
      - Emily Lee with Marge Hoskins and Polly Lane, Image 5007.05.0220